So this is an absurdly useful
representation, which I suppose is why it's
been around for
several thousand years. So those are serpents
back to back, by the way, the yin and
yang symbol.
Yang and yin, what does it mean?
Well, these are central concepts in a
cloud of meaning that,
like the visual field, shades out into,
what would you say, alternative
conceptual territory.
Every word occupies the center of a cloud
of denotations, which are very close,
and connotations, which are farther apart.
When you hear the word, the connotations
echo So which is cauldron and
swamp and darkness and cat,
right? All those things come
together in that concept
and which is the central
is a central component of that cloud
of meaning . and yin are like that. If
you understand them as order and chaos,
you're getting close Now, you know what that
means too It means
determinate order and possibility, right?
That's what the world's made of And that
is what the world's made out
of that's right. That's what
your consciousness deals with
... Mostly your consciousness deals with
the realm of possibility. All things that
are predictable become unconscious. They
disappear from view your consciousness is
literally the
Faculty the spirit that
encounters what is yet to be
Right, right as you practice
something it automatizes
You know that when you first learn to
drive you have to pay attention to every
movement of your hands
every movement of your feet
You can't concentrate on the road
You look right in front of the car as
you become expert all of that disappears
You look half a mile now a quarter of a
mile down the road eighth of a mile because
you can still stop right when
something's that far away you plan your
Destination you run all these
automated routines underneath that's
Not in consciousness unless something goes
wrong right consciousness is an error
detection and correction system
Now that's not all it is, but it's definitely
that and it interacts mostly with the
realm of
Possibility the structure is invisible
Yang is also
Masculinity and yin is femininity I've
got a lot of negative comments about that
idea the first thing I'd
like to say is that's not my
Right this is a very very very very
old idea in fact, it's one of the most
fundamental of old ideas and
If the feminists let's say are allowed
to characterize the masculine as the
patriarchy, which is order
Pathological though it may be then
what's left for the feminine?
Well one L one and answer that is the role
of patriarchal usurper. That's what Eve
does in the Garden of Eden, right?
The other Option is that
there's a separate realm
Right, and that's well, what did we say
already? Why is the unknown feminine?
There's a lot of reasons number one
Women are the biggest
stumbling block to any
Implementation of patriarchal
order what do I mean by that?
Imagine that you embody an element of
the patriarchal spirit as a man and you
act that out in the world and
while you're dating and
That's unsuccessful
Right, that's chaos
That's chaos It's an it's a rebuke to
everything you are not only conceptually but
biologically, right?
It's the ultimate rebuke to that establishment
of order right also the ultimate
potential renewal
Did I do you know the movie Groundhog Day
by any chance Bill Murray? It's a great
movie You could watch that
It would help you with this course
He's a narcissistic weatherman who is?
Compelled to live the same day
over and over until he gets it
Right, which is what we're all
compelled to do by the way
and he falls in love with this beautiful
woman who's kind who's everything he's not
and He has to undergo a
transformation so radical that I
think he tries to kill himself
250 times something like that doesn't work
because he wakes up the next morning at 6
in the morning But he has to reconfigure
who he is so that he becomes attractive
Well, that's a rebuke to
A stale order and so that's part of the
reason that femininity is chaos and
possibility
Let's see
Here's another example Sleeping Beauty the
the Disney movies is a good example of
this It's quite quite a common motif
There's a scene where the Evil Queen
traps Prince Philip in a dungeon and
Tells him that he's going to be held there
until he's old and then she laughs madly
away And so she's the
devouring Oedipal mother in that
situation she's the mother whose
tyrannical love is so complete that it
Exhausts the masculinity of her son who's
never allowed to leave because she loves
him so much
So that's a major rabbit hole And why
does that make itself manifest as a
mythological motif? Well Freud was
alert enough to know that
humans have the longest
dependency period of any
creature 18 years
that
maternal bonding is
incredibly intense and
absolutely vital and
Even in many ways the precondition for
adult romantic relationships because
evolution is a conservative
business and much of the circuitry
That's involved in mother-infant bonding
is also involved in pair bonding
Which is why we might refer to someone we
love who's an adult female as baby for
example
Something
thing, the highest spirits go most dreadfully
wrong when they invert. So Lucifer is
the prideful
intellect, right? Because
in Milton's portrayal of
the battle between good
and evil, Lucifer is the
spirit created by God who flew the highest
and went the most wrong He's the light
bringer He's
the intellect, the prideful intellect
who believes that it can dominate and
determine instead of
being subordinated to the proper upward
oriented harmony that can impose its will,
in which
case it becomes not the highest of
all possible spirits, but the most
pathological, right?
Marx is a great example of that as
far as I'm concerned, and many of the
postmodernists This
unbelievably nihilistic, prideful,
egotistic, hedonistic, self -centered
intellect that wants to recast the entire
world in its
malevolent image. The maternal instinct,
well, if it goes astray, look the hell
out And it's a very
tricky thing to balance because
my daughter, when she was about
three, my son was a year and a half
and he was starting to walk and she
had taken a lot of care of him.
And had bonded very tightly with him. And
we had stopped referring to him as a baby
and she was still referring to him as a baby
And so we said, he's not a baby anymore
Then she had a dream and I was writing maps
of meaning and she came and told me the
dream So I wrote it down She dreamt that
a tree in the forest next to us moved
into our backyard and burnt down and left
a hole So that's a tree of life Okay It
burnt down and left a hole And
then Julian crawled into it.
And there was water in it and he was reduced
to a skeleton and there was a bug in
the water and the bug pulled his skeleton
out and then he reconstituted And so she
told me that dream and it just flattened
me because he's like three years old And
she told it and, you know, the way babies
or the way three -year -olds talk was
pretty simple And then a bug pulled him
out I remember her saying that. And yeah,
Julian drowned and then he turned into
a skeleton and a bug pulled him out
A tree came into our backyard and burned
down and left a hole Well, what's that?
Well, that's something living, right? It's
a fully formed entity that disappears
and leaves a hole with water in it, a
possibility And then there's a renewal Well,
what was she modeling? Well, what was he
if he wasn't a baby? You know, and she was
playing with this terrible conundrum She
loved this baby and now wasn't a baby It's
like, what the hell? And that's
every mother has that problem.
Every mother has that problem And it's
it's continual, right? Because on the one
hand, you have to, especially an infant
before nine months, it's like you have to do
everything for an infant An infant is always
right, right? You just do whatever an
infant wants But then about nine months
when the baby starts to become ambulatory,
then it has to guide its own behavior
increasingly And it has to be encouraged to
move out and to and it has to be subjected
to the restrictions of real mobile life
and social life
And so the mother has to transform
from an agent of complete
care to an agent of encouragement of departure,
right? Which is why it's a very good
idea for a mother to also have her own
life, right? Because seriously, that's a
necessary thing And so
as the impediment to
independence and inverted
maternal love is an
agent of catastrophic care
else And that's that's the evil queen in
Sleeping Beauty, right? She locks the
prince away. Now, what happens to the evil
queen, right? The positive fairies come
along, they're they're feminine, and they
free him So that's that's the positive
feminine possibility that
says, go after the princess,
right? And so he gets on his horse and he
leaves And then the evil queen finds out
And then what does she turn into? A
dragon. And no one minds. Right? So you're
you're You're sitting there
watching that movie and there's
an evil queen and you think,
yeah, well, of course, there's evil queens
And then she turns into a dragon and you
don't bat an eye. You think, well, of
course, she turns into a dragon It's like,
really? That's just a matter of course, is
it? It's like Geppetto ending up in the
whale It just makes sense And now does it?
Well, it does because it's actually the
case that the most brutal impediment
to life and the pursuit of a mate
that a man faces, if
he's a man, he's a woman
If he has an Oedipal mother, it's the
terrible dragon that's her insecurity that
will devour him and fate him
to isolation and death. And
in order to face that, he has to,
what would you say? He has to see
the terrible dragon in her
protestations of love. Brutal.
There's a documentary I would
recommend called Crumb. It's about
this.
Underground cartoonist named Robert Crumb,
who was a big, was a major figure in the
underground movement in San Francisco
in the 1960s And that was his family
If you want to understand serial rapists
and killers, you watch that documentary
and you'll understand them And
that's not a pleasant undertaking.
So it's the only documentary I've ever
seen that got this right And the reason it
happened is because the man who made it.
Was a friend of the family.
And so he got access in a way that
would have otherwise been impossible.
It's brutal.
His brother, one of his brothers, Crumb,
Crumb makes it, you know, very unpopular in
high school He's one of those
boys who was in the category of
dates aren't even an option under
any circumstances whatsoever.
Right So all the women he drew were like
bird headed monsters, very physically
powerful and very judgmental
that's his view of women
and so he's
very resentful
Now, he becomes a very acclaimed artist
and quite successful in his relationship
with women in some ways flips around
he gets married he has a child
he has a life good for Robert Crumb
he came from hell.
His father threw him across the room when
he was five and broke one of his limbs and
was tyrannical
his mother was hooked on amphetamines
and it was a brutal, brutal story.
His brother would go very brilliant
these are all very brilliant men
genius level IQs
there are three brothers.
The brother, the other brother,
the second oldest brother, he
became a serial sexual molester
and would go down to the
financial district in San Francisco, basically
naked in a loincloth and sit on a bed
of nails just as a protest.
Resentful, resentful
beyond belief to the core
his older brother never really left his
high school bedroom, died at about 50.
Six months after the documentary
by drinking furniture polish.
It's rough, but that's the evil queen.
That's chaos. Here's another story
Snow White
you remember the new movie?
Yeah well, so let's walk
through the real Snow White
okay so Snow White has an evil
I think it's a stepmother
why?
Because you're a hundred times more at
risk for abuse if you have a step parent
A hundred times.
Right.
So. Well, why?
Because you're likely to be viewed as a
biological impediment and an obstacle to
time with the person who's
actually the target of affection
that doesn't always happen,
but it happens a lot.
Snow White has the evil queen
okay who's the evil queen?
The evil queen wants to be the beauty,
but it's not her time to be the beauty
because she's 40.
Well, it's her time to do whatever 40
year old women do, which we'll return to.
That beauty
That beauty that drives Snow White towards
the prince, that's young woman destiny,
that's her place in life, and the
evil queen wants to maintain that
beyond its due date, and she does that by
engaging in a sequence of behaviors the
evolutionary psychologists call fertility
suppression, which is the machinations of
women, but older women in particular,
with regards to younger women, to
knock them out of the marriage
So in Islamic countries where
female genital mutilation is the
norm, it's generally
administered by the old women.
Right. And so, yeah, no
kidding. Rough. Okay
So the evil queen in Snow White wants to
be the fairest in the land, and maybe that
would be fine if it didn't come at
Snow White's expense, but it does
and so Snow White has to
contend with this reality.
And so she has to leave because it's...
It's too dangerous and so she goes out into
the forest, which is the unknown, right?
City, walled, medieval.
Outside of that is chaos.
She's out in the forest
and there she's protected by dwarves
now, in the Grimm Brothers fairy
tale, the dwarves don't have names.
And they're not little funny guys that are
useless with a messy house like this new
Snow White
The dwarves keep a very clean house,
and they're very hardworking.
They're ordinary men.
They're ordinary men
men And that means that they're the foundation
of the patriarchy That's a good way
of thinking about it Just the
basic competence that keeps things
going. And they protect her
from the evil
queen. Right. But not completely.
And so the evil queen
comes back in disguise.
And the first thing
she gives Snow White is a bodice. So like
a corset. Okay So what does a corset do?
It exaggerates
waist to hip ratio. And so it's a way
of artificially enhancing fertility
symbols,
but in a manner that's life threatening
So the bodice is so tight that Snow White
just about dies And that happened
in Victorian times when women were
wearing corsets that were very,
very tight and so the evil queen
entices the young woman into
a display of beauty that nearly costs
her her life now the dwarfs can rescue
Snow White from that. And then the evil
queen comes back and she gives her a poison
comb Same thing More narcissistic
self -aggrandizement And the
dwarfs can protect her
from that But then
the evil queen feeds her a poisoned apple
Okay Well, that goes all the way back to
the story of Adam and Eve. To
ingest something is to incorporate
it, to take it in. There's no
difference between Okay
There's no difference between food and
knowledge Okay Why? It took me like ten years
to figure this out
because you trade knowledge for
food. So knowledge is meta food.
So knowledge is worth more than
food you know, if you have...
Your car doesn't work You take it to a
mechanic. He knows what to do You pay him, he
eats.
Right so we substitute knowledge
for food to incorporate is to...
To incorporate is both to eat
in the physical sense,
but also to
Incorporate a metaphood
man does not live by bread alone.
Right? Same idea. Okay
so the evil queen in Snow White feeds
Snow White a pathological doctrine.
And the dwarfs cannot
protect her from that. Right
And so you could give that some serious
consideration in the presence of an absolute
collapse of birth rates around the world.
Right so why is femininity,
yin, chaos, possibility?
Well, here's another reason,
if that's not enough.
In the story of Adam and Eve,
these are complex stories.
Both Adam and Eve are proclaimed
to be made in the image of God
which is really something right?
Because the typical critique, say, of the
biblical corpus is that it's patriarchal
and oppressive
which is an anti-truth
It's a literal inversion of the truth
It's a very old text and...
Really, like, one of the first proclamations
it makes about human beings is that
both men and women are
made in the image of God
which is as egalitarian a
sentiment as you could ever hope
It's not just egalitarian
It's also elevating
That we partake of the same essence as the
spirit of God that sits on the realm of
chaotic possibility and
conjures order out of the void
that's a definition of consciousness.
And that that characterizes
men and women equally.
And then Adam is...
Given a task, like his role
his role is to name, specify, right?
Specify and position.
And that's a patriarchal structure
It's a hierarchical structure.
Say what everything is
God brings things to Adam
to see what he names them.
The name is the thing
It's the functional utility
of the object, let's say
and then to subdue, to put
everything in its order
that's to build that ordering structure.
And Eve means...
Either connecto connecto.
It's It's partner in combat
It's something like optimal
adversary partner in combat.
You can think about it as partner in
play, I think is the best way to get that
because what you want in a marriage
is an optimized challenge.
Right? You don't don't want to push over
you don't want a tyrant
you want someone to contend with
that facilitates mutual development
and so that's the way that the relationship
between men and women is constructed.
And Eve
And Eve is drawn out of Adam
in this representation.
So her role is...
It's outside the boundaries of his role
And I think the reason for that
is the same reason that it's Eve
that's tempted and eats the fruit
I think it's because women have to
stand for those things that are not
included in the current structure
so for example, if you're
married and you have a baby,
then the baby...
Is a newcomer into the order of the little
society that constitutes the marriage and
it's the woman who has to be the mediator
between the baby and the man. She has to
pay attention to
how the baby's needs aren't being served So
she's serving the, it's like Mary in the
Gospels,
she's serving the outsiders. That's a good
way of thinking about it She's serving
and she's the voice for what's
not included in the order And
that gives her a protest
function. And so
I don't think it's fluke at all that in the
universities now the major protesters on
the behalf of the oppressed are female. You
know, it's an inversion of the, it's an
inversion of
the maternal order. These are usually women
between 18 and 34. So childless women
between 18 and 34 stand up on behalf
of the oppressed It's like, really? So
the feminine is the beneficial
antithesis of the current
order, right? And speaking for the manner
in which it needs to be transformed and
expanded. And so, and that can become a
usurping function,
right? And that's what happens with Eve.
So, and then Adam, like, you know, the way
the story lays
itself out is that Eve eats first and then
she offers the fruit to Adam and he just
eats it
Because there's there's nothing
Right? He should, he should have not done
that But he just, he's weak. His weakness
is equivalent
to her sin It's the same thing And then
it's worse because they realize they're
naked Then they've overreached They've
bitten off more than they can chew and their
vulnerability makes itself
manifest to them And now they're terrified
They realize they're going to die They
realize the difference between
good and evil It's a complete
bloody collapse. The next day, God
comes along and asks Adam to
walk with him in the garden.
And Adam hides behind a bush
and refuses to show himself And God, which
is, you know, a comic, that's a comic
interview It's
like God can't see through bushes You know,
it's really not very bright It doesn't
shine a great light on Adam and his
wisdom And God says to Adam, like,
what are you doing? Why aren't you
walking the proper path? And Adam says,
you know, that woman you made for me,
she knocked me off
the path.
And that's, that's brutal It's so pathetic.
It's like, it's ungrateful, first of all
Second, he takes no responsibility
Third, he blames the woman. And
fourth, he calls God out on
his mistake for offering him a
partner. Right? So Eve doesn't
get a great rap in Genesis But
Adam's like, no,
he's no admirable figure. That's for sure
Well, and that's when history starts,
right? That's when the fall makes
itself manifest. And so, I don't know
Is it, see, the thing is, is that it's
in that story, it's Eve that's the first
target of the
temptations of Lucifer, who's
the prideful intellect that
usurps And I think it's got to
be, it's got to be something like the
fact that the maternal is so good in its
fundamental essence
that it has this profound temptation to
overreach Because the usurping idea,
the Luciferian idea is
meditation that goes across centuries about
the nature of evil And it seems to be
something like the insistence that the
worst evil is the best spirit gone most
astray, right? So Lucifer
is the intellect for sure,
because human beings are, what, are
remarkable for our conceptual capacity.
And obviously,
the evil scientist trope, which is, or the
evil magician trope is, or the evil king,
evil brother of the king it's it's the
same trope It's very, very old and indicative
of that prideful intelligence You see
that in Scar in The Lion King, too, who's
smarter than Musafah, but a much more, a
much less well -developed
character. Very common motif, and for good
reason So the intellect goes wrong, and
that's the Luciferian spirit.
And the maternal goes wrong
It's got to be something like
perverse pride in,
see, you shouldn't take
pride in what you're given.
Right? That's why intellectual pride
is such a cataclysmic mistake like,
if you're blessed with an IQ of 160, that's
not your doing. Right? That's something,
that's a talent that you've been granted,
and you have an ethical responsibility to
it It's not something you brandish like a
flag of pride. It's something you watch
carefully for, and
be grateful for, and put into the service
of the proper order. The same goes for the
maternal.
It's because it's such a highlight
of ethical, of what's admirable
ethically when it serves its
proper function, when serving an infant,
for example. It's got to be a temptation to
overgeneralize from that, to take
pride in it, and to make it,
because even in our culture now,
it's compassion is the highest
virtue It's like, sorry, that's evil
queen territory. Right? It's too
much.
Whatever is at the highest place
is not, it's not compassion
It's much more complicated than that. Okay,
so this is very useful to know if you're
reading stories, watching stories, reading
mythology, when you know that landscape,
that the fundamental landscape is chaos
and order, that the moral universe is hell
to heaven, right? And that's good
and evil, that that's a hierarchy
of aim, that the landscape
itself is
pathways, and tools and obstacles, and
friends and foes, and agents of magical
transformation, and that
that's how the world is.
Constituted, right, as this dialectic
between the order that's predictable and
fruitful, and the
chaos surrounding it that's a town in the
middle of a forest that's a country in the
middle of barbarians. That's the flag
planted in a new territory. That's often a
crucifix or a country flag If it's
the English flag, for example, in
North America, it has a cross
on it, there's a reason for that
that signifies the instantiation
of a domain of order that
the
It's the chaos of that new place into a
ordered cosmos and establishes a game that
can be played there in a mode of
perception that will dominate
And that's taking possession of
chaos. And you're
doing that all the time You're doing that
all the time. You learn to notice Chinese
doctors, they diagnose an
imbalance of yin and yang in a
household. Well, I went to the
houses of many of
my clients, and I could diagnose an
imbalance between chaos and order
You can walk into a house and
there are boxes everywhere that
haven't been touched for thirty
years. They're everywhere. And you open a
box and there's everything you can imagine
in the box There's There's pens,
there's there's money, there's
there's scissors, there's
there's photographs
scissors There's photographs. There's there's
no order It's just chaos and every one
of those boxes is a container
of a hundred decisions
that had been avoided The whole place is
full of boxes Don't worry I was here to be
sure to boxes like that, and
everyone there is sick, and the
targeted person is in therapy,
and you walk into the house, and
you think, well, no wonder you're
all ill You're so stressed.
Why? Because all the order around
you is turned into chaos, and we
already know what happens when
you confront chaos involuntarily.
You're stressed, and what happens
when you're stressed? Your
immune system is suppressed, and
then what happens? Well, you're
preyed to all sorts of physical
illnesses, or if
you get something like cancer, it's going
to go astray very rapidly, and not only
that, you're
depressed, and anxious, and without hope,
because you're burned to a crisp by the
stress You've got
no clear pathway forward. It's like, and
the Chinese doctor would come and say,
well, there's too much yin here,
or you go into a house I've been
in houses like this, where
you're a guest,
and you put a cup on the, you
know, little table, the little $25
table, and the hostess runs over
And the hostess runs over with a coaster,
and puts it under the cup, and gives you a
reproving look,
and that's hospitality, and all of the
carpets are vacuumed so that there's lines in
them, and heaven help you if you
happen to put a footprint and
disturb that, and there's just
order
everywhere. So much order that no one gets
to step out of line even a little bit,
and people are just as stressed
in that situation as they are in
the utterly chaotic household,
right? And so what do you want? You want a
balance between chaos and order And what
signifies that?
Play. What signifies that? Meaning, right?
An inviting pathway forward The spirit of
hospitality. In the Old Testament, there's
virtually no virtue that's more elevated
than hospitality, right? Why?
Well, if everyone made everyone
as welcome as possible,
wherever they went, everyone
would be as welcome as possible,
wherever they would go.
Right. So you practice that And how do
you do that? Well, what do you want in a
situation of
hospitality? Well, you want some play in
the system. You want some excitement You
want some adventure You want some
order You want some challenge.
You want to engage in a game
that moves upwards. Well,
that's a healthy place. That's
a completely different way of
contemplating
pathology than we contemplate it
normally with our materialist
outlook in the West Although it's in
concordance with what we understand materially.
Too much disorder. Too much
stress. Right Well, we know the
psychophysiological consequences
of that.
It's over -preparation for action.
It destroys you It ages you. And so
you want it balanced
You want it balanced And then you're
comfortable there and alert and hoping that
something interesting will happen and
there's more to it in the story of Abraham,
who's the father of nations, right? The
spirit of the patriarchy. There's a vignette
where
strangers come to his dwelling and in his
encampment and there's three of them.
And the story insists that they're either
angels or God himself. It's ambivalent.
And he makes, he's hospitable to
them. Extremely hospitable to
them He's had his adventures by
this time and is
quite wise and so he,
he's very hospitable to them. And then he
finds out that their angels are emissaries
of God or God
himself. So what does that mean? Well, it
means that the more hospitable that you
are to people in the proper
manner, the more opportunity will
shine through those people in your
relationship with them The more
possibility will open up for you
of adventure even. And that's
what happens to Abraham. The
angels tell him that God is about
to destroy Sodom and Gomorrah for
their impropriety
Right? Their deviation into chaos It really
is And their lack of hospitality. That's
the major sins of Sodom and
Gomorrah There are others, but
those are the cardinal sins And
Abraham
mediates with God, telling God that it would
be unfair to destroy the cities because
there might be some good people
there And God says, I don't think
there is anyone good there And
Abraham says, well, I'll go
there and I'll see if I can find
anyone good what if I find,
you know, 50? I think he starts
with 50. And God says, well, if
you find 50 good people
in Sodom, I won't destroy the city
And Abraham is bargaining with God
and says 40. And God says,
okay, 40. And Abraham, who's pushy,
says 30 and then 20 and then 10.
And God signals,
I suppose, to Abraham that maybe he's
pushed his luck far enough. And so Abraham
and the angels go
to and Adam goes to Lot's house Lot
is Abraham's nephew in Sodom and
the inhabitants surround the house
and tell Lot that they're going to
rape the visitors. And Lot
offers his daughters. And
that's very stark and outrageous by modern
lights. But in those times,
if you messed with the wrong
stranger, then an army would come
to your city and kill everyone. Right.
So peace was maintained between
dwellings and the possibility of trade
by the inviolable vow of hospitality.
The person under your roof
was under your protection.
Right, so there weren't police, you know,
there was no centralized authority.
So trade and stability between
settlements depended on hospitality.
What happens to Sodom?
Ten good people can't be found
so what's the moral of that story?
Ten people who abide by the
proper path in a corrupt
city can save it from perdition.
And the deeper moral is you're supposed
to be one of those ten, right?
So that's rough, that's rough.
Okay, so that's probably a
good place to stop, I think,
and we could take some questions.
So as humans, we don't know what
goal maximizes enthusiasm by nature
until experience points
us in the direction
How effective is it when someone else's
experience is what guide us, says, say,
like, the Bible?
So one of the things I learned as a clinician,
when I was, or, and as a professor,
when I was facing young people who were
confused and aimless, the question would
arise,
what would you, what do
you want in your life?
What would you like in your life?
It's a very complicated question, right,
because it's kind of a question of
totality.
And so I had to break the
question down to something else
It's something like, where might you look
for guidance when you're trying to find
your way?
Okay, so here's a rule of thumb.
If you don't know what you're
doing, do what other people do.
Right, so then what do other people do?
I tried to formalize that
I have a program, a future authoring
program, that's a formalization of this
how would you broadly
conceptualize your life?
Let's say you kind of have to
get the central tendency right
It's like that abstract conscience
that Jiminy Cricket is to begin with.
Right?
But it's a lot better than nothing.
And so then maybe you can tailor the
generic to your own purposes as you refine.
But you might as well start with the generic,
unless you want to start from scratch,
which I wouldn't recommend
you don't have that long to live
and some other people might have
something to tell you since here you are,
and they lived before you successfully.
Well, what do people do?
Well, they have some form of keeping body
and soul together on the material front.
They have some vocation or some job.
A vocation might be preferable to a job,
but a job is a lot better than nothing.
They have an intimate
relationship, a marriage.
They have friendships.
They pursue their own edification.
They pursue their education.
They avoid the more egregious
temptations, alcoholism
and sexual misbehavior,
I suppose, being first
and foremost among them
that's not an exhaustive list
There's lots of shoals of rocks
you can capsize your ship on
but those are two good ones.
They serve their community.
They attempt to optimize their
functioning physically and mentally
well, there's eight things, you know
It's like, try doing all those.
Or some of them.
Not none of them
how about not none of them?
And maybe flash out a
vision and assume that,
look, maybe you're Picasso.
You know, or part of you is
or you've got some really creative impulse
that's rare, by the way.
Like, people think that
everyone's creative.
That's not true.
It's a personality dimension.
It's openness.
And lots of people are
very, very low in openness.
We tested people's lifetime
creative production.
Okay, so here's how we tested it.
We took 13 domains of
potential creativity.
Creative contribution
dance, literature, music,
architecture, cooking, etc.
Literature, innovation.
You know, I don't remember all 13.
But you get the picture
And then we developed a scale that was
graduated of eight levels of attainment
within each domain.
With zero meaning I have no
training or skill in this domain.
And eight being my productions have met
with international recognition of one form
or another.
Right?
The maximum score would be something
approximating 13 times eight
Although, you know, you could have
repeated eights if you were particularly
outstanding.
Now, the distribution wasn't
a normal distribution, right?
With most people in the middle and some
exceptional people and some low people
It's a Pareto distribution
which meant that some
people had scores of 110.
And they were way over here
sorry.
This was everyone,
Zero 70% of people scored zero.
Right? And the next most
common score was one
and that would be something
like I've taken a music lesson
but like, well, how many
novels have you written?
How many plays have you written?
How many original pieces
of music have you written?
How many buildings have you built?
You know you know what I mean
It's rare.
Now, there are micro
elements of creativity
but we tried to measure them too.
Anyways.
Maybe you're exceptional perhaps
you should pray you're not.
If you are, have at her.
Even if you're exceptional
mostly, you should be
bounded within convention.
If you are exceptional
and you go out on a limb.
You might want to have a place to retreat
to that's kind of stable and ordinary.
So, it's good to
and so, then where might
you find guidance?
Well, that's what mentoring is for right?
It's like, do the things that people do.
If you're miserable and
you don't know what to do
start there
and then you can refine
you can refine and that's fine.
That's part of that process
that dialectical process
between conscience and calling
you know get the target sketched out
and then, you know maybe you can
concentrate on the bullseye.
And if you don't know where to look
look where everyone else looked.
And be happy that you
have that opportunity.
And also, that's the dwarf
scenario in Snow White
Snow White serves the dwarfs
and then she finds a prince.
Right in that order
she's grateful for the ordinary man.
And she serves them
and they protect her from the evil queen.
And that's not nothing.
And then the prince comes.
Right in that order.
That wasn't the Disney version, by the way
The new Disney version.
Another question.
My memory is not precise about this
but I think you wrote Maps of
Meeting back in the 90s sometime.
Published in 99.
I wrote it from 85 to 99.
So, you've had a lot of
years to think about this.
What's changed in your thinking?
At the end of the book.
I was looking for markers
of the pathway forward.
The end of the book
Maps of Meeting ends with a chapter
called The Divinity of Interest
and so, I figured out calling.
Right.
As a marker of orientation.
Right what beckons to you
what grips your interest spontaneously.
Right which is something
to really watch for
because there are things that
you're not interested in at all
and it's very hard to force
yourself to be interested in them
And then there are things that you find so
interesting that you can't help pursuing
them well, that's your calling.
Right and that's the conjunction between
your systems of exploration and the world
right It's a divine parallel
It's a very strange thing
that's the burning bush
in the Moses story right?
Remember, Moses investigates
the burning bush
It's this living phenomenon.
That it's life exaggerated
because a tree is alive
and the fire is metabolism.
And so, it's this intensely burning
phenomenon that calls to him
and he investigates it deeply, deeply.
And a good thing to know in your life is
to pursue one thing as deeply as you can
because you get to the bottom of it
and then the spirit that lies
at the bottom reveals itself.
And that's what transforms you
that's what transforms you into a leader.
Moses is a shepherd he's like a dwarf.
He's an ordinary good man
which isn't all that ordinary
right It's something.
Because a shepherd keeps the
wolves and the lions at bay
and protects the innocent.
Like that's a good
definition of masculinity.
But his intense pursuit of
what calls him off the path.
Because that's what the burning bush does.
His intense pursuit of that shows
him a deeper vision of the world
and then the spirit that's at the
bottom of things speaks to him
and that's what makes him able
to stand up against the tyrant
to specify the promised land
and to lead his people out of captivity.
That's a psychological story as
well as a sociological story.
Okay so I had that part right
although I didn't know the burning
bush segment at that point
I knew that calling was one of the
pathways the divine uses to reveal itself
so to speak
but I didn't understand the
role of conscience as well
I knew then that you had to
be careful with your words
you shouldn't lie I knew that people
like Solzhenitsyn who rebuked the lie
were transformative figures,
But I hadn't formalized it
I didn't know that the divine pathway is
marked by a dialectic between conscience
and calling.
And so I figured that out
over the last couple of years
and that's been in the Old Testament
elijah who is the prophet.
He's taken bodily up to heaven.
He's the only prophet who's
taken bodily up to heaven
it happens with Christ
so it's a very rare occurrence.
And he is the first person
who identifies the divine
with conscience
The still small voice.
He forgoes nature worship.
He's an enemy of the prophets of Baal
who were nature gods
nature god worshippers,
Like the environmentalists of today.
And he realizes that God isn't in the fire
the conflagration,
The forest fire he's not in the hurricane.
He's not in the earthquake
in these awe inspiring
manifestations of the natural world.
That whatever the divine is
is more akin to the voice of conscience
that calls to us in stillness.
That's Elijah's proclamation
It's a revolutionary idea.
It's like Socrates and his daemon
It's a revolutionary idea
that the divine makes itself
manifest in that still small voice.
Right? And that's how Jiminy
Cricket defines his role by the way
as the still small voice
very very interesting these
weird mythological echoes
but the Disney animators
of that time were geniuses
so it's not surprising that they had
The connotative knowledge
that a genius would have
that's a calling too
you know can you imagine them
piecing that story together.
Thinking oh that works
oh that fits.
Do they know why?
No. Not really.
Fits.
You know it
like the fact that Geppetto
ends up in the whale
and they manage to integrate
that into the narrative.
So unlikely. But it fits the pattern.
So.
So that was a further
elaboration that was important.
Most of the rest of it is.
Just further elaboration
of the central themes
I read the audio version
of Maps of Meaning.
And recorded it not long ago
well five years something like that
and I just wrote a new introduction.
There's a 25th anniversary
version coming out.
With quite a lengthy new introduction
where I actually answer
that question in detail.
So.
Most of the insights.
That I developed in that book.
Have stood the test of time
and I think I think the reason for that,
I know the reason for that
is that I didn't write down anything
I couldn't buttress
with at least four or five
different dimensions of evidence.
Like all the things I'm telling you today.
They work in many different scenarios.
Like they're not single evidence
I'm not deriving them from
single points of evidence.
They have to work mythologically
and scientifically.
That's a tough one
to begin with and
And then there's various.
Scientific And philosophical
modes of conceptualization
to unify cybernetic theory
and phenomenology.
And the psychophysiology of perception
and pharmacology.
With the mythological structure.
And to relate that to narrative
that's a lot of cross-referencing
know The probability that
The convergence of those.
Seven things say
six things
is wrong.
I don't think so.
Pretty hard to.
Come up with a.
Solution that fits all those constraints.
So mostly. It's been a matter of
continual elaboration
And deepening of understanding.
So but the but I missed
the role of conscience
I knew it then too
I thought There's
see I never liked Campbell
joseph Campbell's.
Follow your bliss idea
I thought yeah,
No.
Where's the malevolence
and the suffering.
Follow your bliss
mmm.
Little too.
Naive. Californian
buddhist For me.
There's got to be a constraint function.
You know to keep you on the
straight and narrow and.
Enticement is one thing
but a slap on the side of the head
now and then is also pretty damn useful
and you probably need both.
So that dialectic
Makes that's
what did Jung say too
It's analogous.
The classical conception of God
was that he ruled
with two hands mercy And.
Justice.
Mercy alone that's compassion.
Let's say.
It's pathological.
Justice alone It's like
who could prevail
you need that balance
right Because you need
to be held to account
but if it's too stringent
then everyone.
Is unforgivable.
But if it's all mercy
well you can do anything you want dear
and I'll still love you
It's like you don't really love me
if that's that's Joe Biden with Hunter.
Really God.
So so appalling.
There's nothing I can think of
that Would be worse to do
for my son than to.
Provide him with a presidential pardon.
If you really wanted to just.
Destroy your.
Your son that's how you do it.
It's like so brutal,
So brutal.
That was the biggest I
knew that was missing
I knew there was something missing
but it took me a long time
to figure out.
What it was.
All right.